狸
猫
作
品
字幕来源：公映国语听译 & 蓝光原盘校订
中文翻译：狸猫  英文整理：狸猫
时间轴：狸猫  校对：狸猫  后期特效：狸猫
仅供学习交流 勿做商业用途 如需转压引用请保留作者信息
蓝天工作室
《What Is Love》
What is love if it's not with you?
I know when you're alone You feel it too
In your arms is where I long to be
'Cause being with you gives me sanity
Welcome to Rio!
Listen to me, darling
I wake up every morning thinking about the way you feel
I wonder if you know it
And what good is the party If you're not around?
But listen to me now
What good is love?
If it's not your love
Am I your baby love?
Is it a crazy love?
This is a crazy party I'm so glad I'm here with everybody
Baby, move your body Shake it to the ground
Break it, break it, break it down, Blu
Me?
What's a song if you can't hear it too?
Can't imagine dancing without you
A shooting star Ain't really nothing to see
If you're not right here Standing next to me
Listen to me, darling
I wake up every morning
Thinking about the way you feel
I wonder if you know it
What good is the party if you're not around?
Listen to me now
What good is love?
If it's not your love
明尼苏达州来的鸟还有自己的舞步
For a bird from Minnesota, you've got some moves.
这不是舞步 这是事故
That wasn't a move. That was an accident.
不过我接受你的恭维
But I accept the compliment.
多亏拉斐尔能帮我们照顾孩子
It's great Rafael could watch the kids.
是啊，这样今天你得和我在一起..一整晚
Yeah, it looks like you're stuck with me...all night.
你是我的唯一 布鲁
You're my one and only, Blu.
那太好了，因为公的就剩我一个了（...汗!!!）
That's a good thing, since I'm the only other one.
比翼鸟 新年快乐
Hey, you lovebirds! Happy New Year!
拉斐尔 他们在哪？
Rafi? Where are the--
孩子们和路易兹在一起 不用担心！
The kids are with Luiz. No worries!
担心？我们很担心
Worries. Right here.
路易兹 孩子们呢？
Luiz? Where are the kids?
什么？我又没有孩子
What? I don't have any kids.
Jewel & blu - 我们的孩子
Our kids!
哦 对了 我交给小不点了
-Oh, right. I left them with Tiny.
小不点？
Tiny?
干嘛 她可是这里最棒的保姆
What? She's an excellent babysitter.
我是这里最差劲的保姆
I'm a horrible babysitter!
这一定会很炫的
This is gonna be awesome!
行了 我已经计算过了
All right, I've done all the calculations...
每次爆炸都会完美的踩在节奏点上
and each explosion will be perfectly synced to the beat.
除非我没有算上这个...
Unless I didn't carry the one.
我们这里会有...
Here's my vision.
红色 蓝色 绿色 黄色...紫色
Red, blue, green, yellow, yellow! Purple.
我觉得应该是...
Here's my vision. Boom! Crash! Bang! Kapow!
我觉得你们爸妈不会想看到这个的
I don't think your parents would like this very much.
那我们开始吧
Here we go.
你这是要去哪儿啊小鸟
Where are you going, little bird?
-这是什么？ -哦 爸爸
-Hey, what is this? -Oh, Dad.
你们知道规矩的
Guys, you know the rules.
没有大人的监督 不能放烟花
No pyrotechnics without adult supervision.
我们问过小不点了
We asked Tiny.
这就更糟了 抱歉小不点
That's even worse. Sorry, Tiny.
工钱我不要了 布鲁先生
You don't have to pay me, Senhor Blu.
下次玩 一定要先问我
Kids, next time, ask me.
可你每次都说不
But you always say "no."
不 我没有
No, I don't.
爸爸 你在否认现实
Dad, you're in denial.
好吧 亲爱的 我经常说不嚒
Honey, do I always say "no"?
-是的 我是说...不... -太好了
-Yes. I mean, no. -Great.
现在妈妈也在说不了
Now Mom's saying it, too.
听着 我们是地球上最后的蓝皮克斯金刚鹦鹉
Listen, we are the last blue Spix's Macaws left on the planet.
我们得注意安全 有蓝色羽毛的鸟
We have to stay safe. Birds of blue feathers...
要团结在一起
Have to stick together.
我闻到烤鸡味了
I smell chicken.
啊 不不不....
No, no, no!
根据我的计算 这是他今天说的第27个不了
By my calculations, that's his twenty-seventh "no" today.
救命 啊...
Help!
-5..4..3..2..1.. -大家伙 快跑
-Five, four, three, two, one! -Everybody, fly!
新年快乐
Happy New Year!
这不公平 凭什么只有爸爸玩的这么爽
Oh, man. How come Dad gets to have all the fun?
看啊 成功了
Look! It worked!
看来今年开了个好头
Well, this year is off to a great start.
里约大冒险 2
RIO 2
蓝天工作室继《冰河世纪》后第二部系列长篇动画
亚马逊之行 第七天
Amazon Expedition, day seven.
距里约热内卢 2000英里
Two thousand miles from Rio...
我们到达热带雨林的中心
we've reached the center of the rainforest.
当我们沿着河流毫不费力的向前划行的时候
We are surrounded by plants and animals...
到处都是...
struggling for survival...
挣扎求生的植物和动物
as we glide effortlessly down the river.
毫不费力的是你
Effortless for you.
哇哦 好漂亮
How pretty.
吐出来 快吐出来
Spit it out, spit it out!
我们已经接近亚马逊树林鹌鹑的栖息地
We are near the nesting grounds of the Amazonian Wood Quail.
六个月前我们从走私者手中救下这只小鸟
Six months ago, werescued this little bird... from smugglers.
那时候它生着病，营养不良
It was sick, malnourished...
还断了一条腿 而现在...
with a broken leg, but now...
我可靠的助手..
my trusty assistant--
我是说我的妻子兼同事 将要把它..
I mean, loving wife and colleague, will release her...
放归回丛林
back to her natural habitat.
都没事了 你可以走的 就像这样
It's okay. You can go now. Just like this.
还是让我跟他说吧
Let me talk to her.
走吧
Go on.
FREAKS!
你觉得他会没事吗
Do you think she's gonna be all right?
给他一点时间
Give it some time.
欢迎回家
Welcome home.
等一下 它..好像在说什么 图里奥
Wait a minute. What is she saying, Tulio?
他是不舍得我们 在和我们说再见
It's just hard for her to say goodbye.
不
No.
我觉得他好像在警告我们
I think she's trying to warn us.
不不不 琳达
No, no, no, Linda.
这可能是吸引异性的舞蹈
It might be some sort of mating dance.
图里奥 看那
Tulio! Look!
快划 快啊
Paddle! Now!
好的 好的 划
Okay, okay, okay. Paddle.
小心！
Watch out!
快划 快划 往后 往后
Paddle, paddle! Backward, backward!
往右 不不 往左 向前 不！
To the right! No, left! Forward, forward! No, no!
你想清楚再说 图里奥
Make up your mind, Tulio!
这下可糟了
Cheese and sprinkles!
哦 不！
Oh, no!
划 快划啊 快点
Paddle, paddle! Faster!
图里奥
Tulio!
琳达 琳达
Linda! Linda!
图里奥
Tulio!
感谢上帝 你没有事
Thank heavens you're okay.
图里奥 这是..
Tulio, is that a--
啊 琳达 真难以置信
Linda! This is incredible!
《Breakfast in Rio》
早上好 珠儿
Good morning, Jewel!
嘿 你们看我找到了什么
Hey! Everyone, look what I found.
布鲁？
Blu?
孩子们？
Kids?
大家都去哪儿了...？
Where did everybody...?
好了 谁肚子饿了想吃早饭
Okay, who's ready for some breakfast?
难以置信
Unbelievable.
你知道么
Did you know...
那些全麦煎饼所含的维生素矿物质
that these whole wheat pancakes have twice the vitamins and minerals...
是普通煎饼的两倍
of regular pancakes?
而且加上蓝莓后味道会好上4倍
And with the blueberries, it's four times as tasty.
嘿 蓝莓都哪去了
Hey, where are the blueberries?
哦 爸爸
Oh, Dad!
在找这个吗？
Looking for this?
给我吧
Bring it.
已经到了最后关头 他的脚仿佛有魔力一样
It's down to the final minutes. He's got magic in his feet!
他射门了
He shoots!
得分了 球进了！
-He scores! Goal! -Goal!
噢耶 我接到了 我真是太棒了
Yeah, I got it. I'm good.
爸爸 注意了
Heads up, Dad!
啊哦
No.
帅呆了
Awesome.
嗨  妈妈
Hi, Mom.
这下惨了
Busted.
该走了
Time to go.
亲爱的 你饿了吗
Hey, honey. Hey. You hungry?
布鲁 我跟你说过的
Blu, we talked about this.
是吗 我不记得了
Did we? I don't--
哦 对的 你拿的是什么
Yeah, so, what do you got there?
早饭
Breakfast.
很好笑 不过 说真的 这是什么
That's funny. But seriously, what is that?
这是个巴西栗
It's a Brazil nut.
没想过离城市这么近的地方居然也有
I never thought I would find one this close to the city.
我要教孩子们怎么打开
I wanna show the kids how to open one.
你是说打开这个吗
You mean like this?
爸爸已经教过我们了
Dad already showed us.
等等 来了
Wait. Wait, go back.
爸爸妈妈
Mom! Dad!
你们上电视了
You're on TV!
巴西鸟类学家图里奥蒙泰罗博士
Doctor Tulio Monteiro, the Bird Man of Brazil...
今天宣布了一项重大发现
announced an important discovery today.
我们相信 我们在亚马逊丛林深处找到了野生的
We believe we have encountered a wild blue Spix's Macaw...
蓝色金刚鹦鹉
deep in the Amazon jungle.
蓝色金刚鹦鹉之前被认为在野外全部灭绝了
The blue Spix's Macaw was thought to be practically extinct...
仅存的一家鹦鹉
with the last remaining family living under protection...
目前居住在里约的布鲁鸟类保护区
at the Blu Bird Sanctuary in Rio de Janeiro.
我们出名了
We're famous!
如果找到这些野生鹦鹉 他们的家园将受到保护
If these birds can be found, their home will be saved.
那里可能有很多这种鹦鹉
There may be a whole flock out there.
如果真的有 我们会找到他们 并保护他们
And if there is, we will find them and protect them.
你好 布鲁
Hi, Blu!
你好 琳达
Hi, Linda!
我们不是唯一的
We're not the only ones.
我们还有活着的同类啊
There are more of us out there.
是啊 太好了 我相信...
Yeah, that's great. I'm sure they're--
这么长时间 我一直....
All this time, I thought...
我一直以为...我们是孤独的
I thought we were alone.
嘿 以前也没有那么糟糕
Hey, it hasn't been all bad.
是挺好的 可是...
Of course not.
可是想象一下 有一大群同类
But just imagine if there was a whole flock of us.
那该有多么美妙啊
How amazing would that be?
-我们得做点什么 -真的吗
-We gotta do something. -We do?
对 我们去亚马逊 去帮助琳达和图里奥找到他们
Yeah, we have to fly to the Amazon and help Linda and Tulio find them!
哦...我们不能说走就走
Whoa, we can't just pack up and go.
为什么不能
Why not?
现在正是时候出去让翅膀吹吹风了
It's about time this family got a little air under our wings.
看看我们 音乐播放器 电视 煎饼
Look at us. iPods, TV. Pancakes?
亲爱的 我们不是人类 我们可是鸟
We're not people, we're birds.
我们应该回到野外 做真正的鸟 布鲁
We have to get out into the wild and be birds, Blu.
让孩子们回到大自然吧
Let the kids connect to their roots.
看看我们从前的生活
Show them what I had.
他们需要这样 我们也需要
They need this. We need this.
来吧 布鲁！你说呢？
Come on, Blu, what do you say?
我不知道...
I don't know.
也许吧...
Maybe.
他没有说“不”
He didn't say "no."
这就意味着他说 行
Which means he practically said "yes."
-嘿 等一下 -亲爱的 一定会很好玩！
-Hey, wait a sec-... -It's gonna be so much fun!
耶...
Yeah!
我们要去亚马逊咯
We're going to the Amazon!
等一下，亚马逊是什么？
Wait. What's the Amazon?
亚马逊 目前世界上最濒危的生态系统之一
The Amazon is one of Earth's most endangered ecosystems...
由于非法砍伐和耕种
due to illegal logging and farming.
我们希望博士和他的团队
Let's hope Doctor Monteiro and his team...
能找到那些珍惜鸟类 让他们的家园得以保存
can find these rare birds so their home can be saved.
那里可能有很多这种鹦鹉
There may be a whole flock out there.
如果真的有 我们会找到它们并保护他们
And if there is, we will find them and protect them.
Ecochatos 把我的船准备好
Ecochatos Get my boat ready.
我要亲自去处理这件事情
I need to deal with this personally.
下一个
Next!
轮到我了 行了你们可以回家了
That would be me. Okay, everybody can go home now.
你们正在看着的下一位 狂欢之王
You're looking at the next King of Carnival!
嘿 大鸟 祝你好运
Hey, big bird! Break a leg!
走路小心点，别躺着进去！
Walk it off, buddy!
You can't see it coming
You won't find it anywhere else
太精彩了
That was amazing!
伊娃 我亲爱的 你一个音也没落下 伙计们？
Eva, darling, you hit every note. Huh, guys?
是啊 还多了很多我从来没听过的音
Yeah, along with a bunch of notes I never heard of.
拉斐尔
Rafi!
别 别担心 我会和他们说的
Don't worry. I'll talk to them.
我会为你找到完美的角色！
We'll find the perfect spot for you.
嗯...潜规则也没用（意为南极洲演出的角色）
Antarctica, maybe.
最好如此
You better.
回头见 孩子们！
Bye, boys.
我们家里见，我的美味小芒果
See you back at home, my tasty mango!
哎...这些表演一点都不好 我连一点灵感都没有
None of these acts are inspiring. I'm just not inspired.
狂欢节眼看就要到了 我们的名声会毁于一旦的
Carnival is right around the corner, and our reputations are on the line.
明白！
Copy that.
我们需要一些能让我们嗨起来的节奏
We need something that can make us wiggle. Something that make us jiggle.
我们需要 动感 火爆 激情
We need something that pops.
你知道火爆怎么说？
You know what "pop" is backwards? Pop.
啪...下一个...
Next.
布鲁
Blu?
对不起兄弟
Sorry, bro!
没关系 路易兹 我也很高兴见到你
It's okay, Luiz. Good to see you, too.
听着 布鲁 我们在寻找一位歌手
Listen, Blu, we are looking for a singer...
一个舞者 样样都会的
a dancer, the whole package.
不要唱歌跑调 跳舞摔跤的
Yeah, and you're more of a mumbler-shuffler.
你懂我的意思么？
You catch my drift?
我不是来面试的 我有事情要宣布
No, I'm not here to audition. I've got news.
我准备要去亚马逊了
I am going to the Amazon.
亚马逊 那可真够野的
The Amazon? Wow, that's wild.
是呀 珠儿觉得这对我们有好处
Yeah, Jewel thinks it'll be good for us.
有多野？
How wild?
超级宇宙无敌野
Real wild.
那里的蚊子能够一口吸干你的血
They got mosquitoes that suck your blood like Slurpees.
那里的蛇能一口将你整个吞下去
Snakes that can swallow you whole.
那里还有吃肉的食人鱼 会吃肉的！
Flesh-eating piranhas that...eat flesh.
哦！好极了 真不赖 我不去了
Great, that sounds really nice. I'm not going.
得了伙计们
Guys, guys, guys.
布鲁 你根本不用担心这些
Blu, you have nothing to worry about.
他们说的这些都有点夸张的过分了
All those stories are highly exaggerated.
-你真的这么想？ -当然了！
-You think so? -Of course!
如果这对珠儿很重要 那你就去吧
If this is important to Jewel, just do it.
老婆开心 日子舒心...一定要记住
Happy wife, happy life. Remember that.
好的 你说的对！
Okay, yeah, you're right.
就当全家一起去度个小假 一定很有趣
A little family vacation might actually be fun.
再说了 又不是定居在那里
Plus, it's not like it's forever.
这就对了
That's the spirit.
好的
Yeah. Okay.
谢谢伙计们
Thanks, guys.
过段时间见
See you in a couple of weeks!
一路顺风 布鲁
Safe travels, Blu!
记得带纪念品回来
Bring me back a souvenir!
得了 他不会回来了 他一定会挂在那里的
Dawg, he ain't coming back. He is dead.
亚马逊！
Amazon!
我们走 快点爸爸 快点
Let's go! Come on, Dad! Come on!
好的 驱虫剂 净水剂 还有创可贴
Okay. Bug spray, check. Water purifier, check. Band-Aids.
-哦 我好像忘了点什么 -酷！
-I feel like I'm forgetting something. -Cool!
是多功能探险小刀
The all-in-one adventurer's knife!
这个还是我来弄吧
I'll be in charge of this.
这不是给你准备的
That's not for you.
嘿 爸爸 来看我这个
Hey, Dad, look at this.
你知道亚马逊的蛇能一口把你吃掉吗？
Did you know the Amazon has snakes that can swallow you whole?
事实上这些故事写得太夸张了
Actually, Bia, all those stories are highly exaggerated.
不一定吧 你看看
No, really. Look.
哦 这个好恶心啊
That's sick!
准备好出发了吗？
All right, are we ready to go?
-你带了个腰包？ -是的
-A fanny pack? -Yeah.
琳达给我的 用来装GPS
Linda gave it to me. I need it for the GPS.
哦 我的GPS呢？
Where's the GPS?
卡拉 我们要走啦
-Hey! -Carla, we're leaving.
我才不去呢！肯定很无聊
I'm not going. It's gonna be lame.
行了 找到了
Okay, here it is.
它有语音识别功能 很好用的 你看着
The voice recognition makes it totally foolproof. Here, watch this.
给我找琳达和图里奥
Find Linda and Tulio.
正在搜索 去东京吃料理
Searching for "Dinner in Tokyo."
好的 额 事实上这个还真不错
Okay. Actually, that does sound like a nice suggestion.
-你相信这个女人？ -是的 我相信
-You trust this woman? -Yes, I do.
嘿 等下伙计们
Hey, wait up, family!
我们也要一起去
I'm coming, too!
别担心哥们 我们会罩着你的
Don't worry, buddy. We got your back.
你老婆让你去了吗？
Eva let you come?
当然！我答应她在狂欢演出里给他弄个角色
Sure. I promised her a spot in the Carnival show.
-答应他什么  -你们迟到了
-You did what? -You guys are late.
-是有点晚！-但我们可是音乐家
-Clock-late. -But musician-early.
等等 你们也要去吗？
Wait, you guys are coming?
我们当然不会错过
We wouldn't miss it for the world.
我们要去丛林寻找最棒的歌手
We gonna scout the wildest, coolest talent in the jungle!
这是我们今年狂欢节演出的创作灵感
It's our inspiration for this year's Carnival show.
狂野的...亚马逊
"Amazon Untamed."
酷
Cool!
我是说...好吧 我也会去的
I mean, yeah. Okay. I guess I'll go.
去亚马逊放手一搏
Amazon jungle or bust, baby!
都准备好去热带探险了么
Who is ready for a tropical adventure?
-一切准备就绪 -出发咯
-All right! -Let's go, birds!
等等 孩子们 还没有点名 等下
Wait, we didn't do a head count. Hey, guys, wait up!
重新规划路线
Recalculating.
嘿 小鸟 快回来
Hey, birds! Come back!
又是这样 丢下我自己走了！
They left without me. Again!
太让人伤心了！
That's messed up.
《O Vida》
里约热内卢
欧鲁普雷图
巴西利亚
前方道路 拥堵
Heavy traffic ahead.
多谢了 GPS小姐
Great. Thanks a lot, GPS lady.
快点 快点 快点
Faster, faster, faster!
慢点....
Slower! Slower! Slower!
我们到了孩子们，这里就是亚马逊的大门了
Here we are, kids. The gateway to the Amazon.
生存
"To be...
还是....毁灭
"or not to be...
这是个问题
"that is the question.
究竟哪一个更高贵 去忍受这命运
"Whether 'tis nobler in the mind...
还是去忍受着无尽的烦恼
"to suffer the slings and arrows of outrageous fortune...
经受无边的摧残
"or to take arms against a sea of troubles...
还是把它忘个干净
"and, by opposing, end them."
噢 真实太美妙了 奈杰尔
That's beautiful, Nigel.
这是什么意思
What does it mean?
死亡 噶比
Death, Gabi.
说的是死亡
It's about death.
哦 奈杰尔 我爱死你的阴沉忧郁了
Nigel, I love it when you get all dark and brooding.
嘿 笨鸟 该上场了
Hey, bird. It's show time!
我的观众正等着我呢
My audience awaits.
从里约的丛林 到亚马逊的街头
From the streets of Rio, to the Amazon jungle...
有请 神秘的大鸟
the bird of mystery!
-丛林火蚁 -别害羞
-Fire ants! -Don't be shy!
来了解下你的命运吧
Learn your destiny!
喂 别打蚂蚁的主意 干你的活去
Hey! Get away from those! Back to work.
妈妈 我要玩这个 占卜
Mommy, Mommy, I want one! I want a fortune!
欢迎光临 夫人
Welcome, madame.
这只神奇的鹦鹉 能够揭示你的未来
This amazing cockatoo will reveal your future.
好了小鸟 选一个吧
All right, bird. Pick a fortune.
快点 小鸟
Come on, bird.
你干的很好 奈杰尔
You're doing great, Nigel.
快一点
Pick it already.
加油 伙计们 就快到了
Come on, gang. Almost there.
今天不用再飞了 晚一点 我们能赶上一艘船
No more flying today. We've got a boat to catch.
根据GPS的计算 明天一早我们就能到
According to my little friend here, this boat will get us there by morning.
他能活下来 但永远也飞不起来了
He'll live, but he'll never fly again.
-快点 小鸟 -快给我算命
-Come on, bird. -I want my fortune!
很好奈杰尔
You're doing great, Nigel.
怎么要这么长时间
What's taking so long?
你这是怎么了
What's the matter with you?
我会这么惨 都是那只蓝色的鸟害的
That blue bird caused my misery.
小鸟乖
Nice birdie?
为什么要打自己 为什么要打自己
Why are you hitting yourself? Why are you hitting yourself?
哇哦 奈杰尔好有男子汉气概
Wow. Nigel is muy macho.
谢谢
Thank you.
我自由了
I'm free!
这里有只箭毒蛙
Poison frog!
嘎嘎叫的凤头鹦鹉 呐喊着要去复仇
The croaking cockatoo doth bellow for revenge.
这是莎士比亚写得
That's Shakespeare, by the way.
没有你的表演 他一文不值
Without your performance, it's nothing.
说得好
Fair point.
一个完成旧任务的好时机
哦 这空气 又清新 又舒适
This air! It's so fresh and full.
再见了 城市里的雾霾
Goodbye, stinky city air!
对！再见！
Yeah, bye.
嘿 谢谢你能为我这样做
Hey. Thank you for doing this.
真的很谢谢你
I really appreciate it.
为了你 我愿意做任何事情 你知道的 对吗？
I would do anything for you. You know that, right?
我当然知道
Of course I do.
我们不是来这吃点心的 我们是来复仇的
We aren't here to snack. We are here to avenge.
等那些讨厌的乘客一睡着
Once these pesky passengers fall asleep...
我们就好好关爱下我的蓝色朋友们 给他们一点..
we'll show our blue friends some love. Some...
毒爱
poisonous love.
哦 这个我最拿手了
That's my specialty.
我们在午夜发动攻击
We attack at the midnight hour...
这样显得更加邪恶
because it's more evil.
保持警惕
Stay alert.
午夜！袭击的时间
Midnight! Time to attack.
奈杰尔 奈杰尔
Nigel! Nigel?
看看我们两个另类的生物
Look at us. Misfits.
一只剧毒的青蛙 一只不会飞的怪鸟
A toxic frog, and a flightless freak.
我们如此的不同 又如此的相同
So different, and yet, the same.
亲爱的 当你睡着了 我们是朋友 那样很好
My darling, while you sleep All is well
可是有个秘密一定要告诉你....
We are friends, and that's swell But the truth is that I have a secret to tell
我爱你
I love you
《Poisonous Love》
人们说这不对 很可笑
People say it's wrong It's absurd
一只青蛙怎么和鸟恋爱 可我心里知道
That a frog and a bird are in love But I know in my heart
这是命中注定的
This was so meant to be
如果我们能拥抱亲吻 那真是天堂般的幸福
If only we could hug and could kiss It'd be heavenly bliss
可你的肺会烂掉 就像这样
But your lungs would explode And you'd lookjust like this
你会窒息 脸涨成蓝色
And you'd gag With your face turning blue
哦...
Eww
不过亲爱的 我会照顾你 我会的 你尽管放松
But, darling, I'll protect you I will, don't worry, just chill
因为我能杀掉任何鸟 只要是为了你
'Cause there isn't a bird That I wouldn't kill
你看不出来吗
For you Can't you see
我们注定要在一起
We were destined to be?
因为我们的爱
-For we have love -Love
有毒的爱...-爱...
-Poisonous love -Love
虽然 是的
And although, yes
我知道你没法拥抱我
I know that you can't hold me
投入我的怀抱吧
Feel me close now.
你爱的翅膀 围绕着我
Your loving wings enfold me
命运告诉我
Fate told me
爱...
Love
有毒的爱...
-Poisonous love -Love
站在这里
Standing here
你离我是如此的近 可是
You're so near And yet
又那么远
So far
就像一颗星星
Like a star.
我们到了
Here we are
哪儿？
Where?
该怎么办
What to do?
怎么办
To do
噢..
Oh, pooh.
你是我的罗密欧 我是你的朱丽叶
You're my Romeo I'm Juliet
我们天生一对 可是
We're so perfect, and yet
如果我们触碰哪怕一点点
If we touch, not by much
可以确信一点
Still on all you can bet
那就是 永别
It's goodbye
我会哭泣
And I'll cry
因为你已不再
As you die
死于我们有毒的 爱...
From our poisonous love
好可怕的梦
What a nightmare.
查理 你应该把我叫醒的
Charlie! You were supposed to wake me!
要行动了
It's time.
能做奈杰尔的搭档真好
I love being on Team Nigel!
我想不出什么比在夜晚下 给乘客下毒更浪漫的事情了
I can't think of anything more romantic than poisoning passengers on a moonlight cruise.
住手
Stop.
那家伙是我的
That one is mine.
一闪一闪小布鲁...
Twinkle, twinkle little Blu.
找你找得好辛苦...
How I wondered, where were you?
高高挂在天空中...
Up above the world so high...
今天让你..
are you ready...
一命呜呼
to die?
你应该吃块绿箭薄荷糖
You need a breath mint.
你睡着了都要嘲笑我！
Even in sleep, you mock me.
等等我
Wait for me!
别丢下我
Don't leave me!
迪耶戈 别到处乱跑
Tiago! Stop fooling around.
我什么也没干啊
I didn't do anything.
孩子 听你妈妈的话
Tiago Gunderson, listen to your mother.
哦 天啊
Man.
我们快到了
We're almost there, right?
-等一下伙计们 -跟上 布鲁
-Hey, guys. Wait up. -Come on, Blu.
记住 有蓝色羽毛...
Remember, birds of a...
算了...
Nevermind.
他们都跑了
They're getting away!
快醒醒 你这个吃蚂蚁的笨蛋 快跟上他们
Wake up, you insect-eating idiot. Follow them.
好多了 现在给我快一点
Better. Now go ten times faster.
这个笨蛋！
River hogs!
你！
You!
我一直在想你是不是比猴子还笨
I always suspected you were dumber than a monkey.
现在我懂了
And now, I know.
老板 您来丛林里干什么？
Boss! What are you doing in the jungle?
你应该问..
Perhaps the better question is...
他们来这里干什么
what are they doing?
那些环保狂
Nature freaks.
这里有几百万平方英里的丛林
Two million square miles of jungle...
可他们偏偏跑到这里来
and they're playing in my backyard?
我可不是好惹的家伙
I don't think so.
你也知道 朋友 我们的伐木作业稍微有一点...
As you know, my friends, this logging operation is a little...
违法
illegal.
如果这些人找到那些鸟 我们的生意就完了
If those two nuts find those birds, we're out of business.
所以你现在要...
And that's why you...
尽快结束他们的寻鸟丛林探险
must put an end to their little bird-watching expedition.
找到他们 赶走他们
Find them and get rid of them.
其余的人 都给我砍树去
The rest of you, go cut some trees.
谁在乎一群什么破鸟
Who cares about a bunch of birds?
鹦鹉会把鸟巢筑在巴西栗树附近
The macaws should be nesting near the Brazil nut trees.
所以我觉得我们应该...
So, I think that we should continue with go--
图里奥 你在听我说话吗
Tulio! Are you listening to me?
你已到达目的地
You have reached your destination.
看！是不是很管用 我们到了
You see? It works like a charm. Here we are.
这是哪？
Where?
嗯 这东西稍微有点误差
These things have a margin of error.
我跟你说过别相信那个女人
I told you not to trust that woman.
这是一个幼虫 他就要进入变蛹的阶段了
That's a Heliconious larva. It's about to enter the pupa stage.
哈 你说桶
You said "poop!"
嘿 孩子们跟紧了
Hey, kids. Stay close.
我去找孩子
I'll get them.
好吧 你们留在这里别动 我去周围看看
Okay, you guys stay put. I'll look around.
别担心 我们就在这 我们哪儿都不去
No worries. We'll be here. We're not going anywhere.
我后背的羽毛都竖起来了
My feathers is popping up on the back of my neck.
我可不喜欢这个感觉
I don't like this.
我们掉头吧
Let's back it up.
比亚 迪耶戈
Bia? Tiago?
拜托 小姐
Come on, lady.
别让我失望 规划前往...秀场的路线
-Don't let me down. -Calculating route to "Funky Town."
好吧 太好了
Oh, great.
好的 伙计们
Okay, guys!
伙计们？
Guys?
呵呵 可以 这很好玩
Good one, guys. Very funny.
很好 很好 很聪明的玩笑
Good, good. Very witty.
珠儿 你在哪？
Jewel, where are you?
孩子们 老婆？
Kids? Jewel?
啊 蓝色金刚鹦鹉
It's a Macaw!
琳达
Linda!
放开我
Let me go!
放开我 你这个野蛮人
Let me go, you heathens!
布鲁？
Blu?
我发誓 这声音听起来像布鲁的
I swear that sounded like Blu.
不 不可能 琳达
That's impossible, Linda.
他在家里 既舒适又安全
He's back home in Rio, safe and sound.
我可是美国公民 你这个野蛮人
I am an American citizen, you savage!
我要求见美国大使
I demand to see my ambassador!
我知道我有这个权利
I know my rights! I know my rights!
退后 野蛮人
Back. Back, you barbarian!
对 没错
Yeah, that's right.
这是个勺子 也是个叉子
It's a spoon and a fork.
害怕了吧 怕的发抖了吧
Be afraid! Be very afraid.
啊哦...把你的东西放下
Whoa! Whoa, buddy. Put the spork down.
放开我...有种来啊
-Let me go! -Bring it!
你应该感到幸运 我不是大个子
Come on! You lucky I ain't big.
真不敢相信 我们找到他们了
I can't believe we found them!
严格的说 是他们找到了我们
Technically, they found us.
好吧 得找点东西来写名字
Okay, we're gonna need some nametags.
你好呀
Hello. Okay.
哦 那是绿箭薄荷糖 你用不到它
No, those are breath mints. Not that you need one.
不过味道还不错...你可以试试
But they're good. You eat them.
不 别连盒都吞下去
No, no, no! Not the whole box.
赶快..把它..吐出来（还记得第一部里珠儿还有布鲁么？）
Get that out of your mouth!
出什么事情 怎么了？
What is this doing here? What's going on?
我们发现他们飞得离人类太近
We found them flying too close to the humans.
-什么 你是谁？ -额..
-What? And who are you? -Uh...
额 可不是一个合适的回答
"Uh" is not an appropriate answer.
我问你话呢 你们到底从哪来
I asked you a question. Where did you come from?
-嘿 退后 你干什么
Hey! Back off!
不好意思小姐...
Hey, excuse me, young lady.
真不敢相信
I can't believe it.
这...这怎么可能
How is this...?
伐木工来的时候
When the loggers came...
到处都是大火 浓烟
there was fire, and so much smoke.
我把你藏在翅膀下面 然后你就...
I had you under my wing, and then you were...
不见了
Gone.
我一直在找你
I've looked everywhere for you.
我在这
I'm here.
爸爸
Daddy!
爸爸？
"Daddy"?
我好想你
I missed you.
没事了 一切都过去了
It's okay. It's okay, now.
有爸爸在
Daddy has you.
看看你 我的小女儿
Look at you.
已经长大了
It's my little girl, all grown up.
长得这么漂亮
You're so beautiful.
就像你的妈妈一样
Just like your mother.
对不起 我把你弄丢了
I'm so sorry I lost you.
我无法想象这些年你一个人到底怎么过来的
I can't imagine you alone, all this time.
没什么 爸爸 我不孤单
No, it's okay, Dad. I wasn't alone.
布鲁找到我了
Blu found me.
很高兴见到你 先生
Sure is nice to meet you, sir.
把翅膀收起来 布图
Tuck that wing away, Stu.
-到我这里来 -当然 近一点
-Now, come here. -Right, sure. Okay.
-是吗？ -再近点
-Closer. -Really?
近一点
Closer.
你把我女儿带回来了 我谢谢你
You brought my Jewel back to me. I thank you.
-现在我要拥抱你 -额 好的
-I'm gonna hug you now. -Okay.
-行了 过来吧   -抱上了
-Now, come here, you. -Okay. There we are.
真是我的荣幸
My pleasure.
尼克 你在哭吗？
Nico. You crying?
看到这么感人的场面让我内心很脆弱啊
It's a heavy moment, and I'm very vulnerable right now.
过来 我们拥抱吧
Come here. Let me get you a hug.
妈妈 你没事吧
Mom, are you okay?
妈妈？我当外公了
"Mom"?
我当外公了
I'm a grandpa? I'm a grandpa.
看看 我是外公了
Look at me, I'm a grandpa!
爸爸 这是卡拉 比亚 迪耶戈
Daddy, this is Carla, Bia and Tiago.
你好呀 先生
Nice to meet you, sir.
不要叫我先生 我的小姐
There is no "sir" around here, young lady.
你应该叫我...怕怕    -怕怕
-You will call me "Pop-Pop!" -Pop-Pop.
哦 我喜欢 我喜欢这么叫你
I like that. It's got a nice ring to it.
我是外公啦 太好啦  我是外公啦
I am a Pop-Pop! Yeah, I'm the Pop-Pop-Pop.
别把外公弄伤了 孩子们
Kids, go easy on old Pop-Pop.
你还叫我先生
You can call me "sir."
我女儿回来啦
My daughter has returned!
这些年我们东躲西藏 人类把我们逼往
For years, we have been on the run...
越来越深的丛林
as the humans push us deeper into the jungle.
不过你看 我们找到了一个避难所
But as you can see, we have found sanctuary.
我们终于可以在这里扎根了
A place we can finally put down roots.
大伙们 出来吧
Everyone! Come on! Everyone, out of your nests!
我女儿回来啦
My daughter is home!
出来吧小鸟们  我的珠儿回来啦
Come on, birds. My Jewel is back!
珠儿？
Jewel?
让开  让开 珠儿！
Make way. Make way! Jewel!
咪咪婶婶  咪咪婶婶
Aunt Mimi? Aunt Mimi!
哦 我想死你了
I missed you so much!
我的小野花终于回家了
My little wildflower has returned!
我就知道你会回来 我用鸟粪算过命了
I knew you were coming back. I saw it in the droppings.
看看这些小家伙们
And look at the little ones!
谁是可爱的小蓝皮克斯鹦鹉
Aren't you the fluffiest, most delicious little macaws?
-哦 你长得可有点着急啊 -哦 咪咪
-You're big for your age. -Mimi...
这是苏
this is Sue.
-事实上我叫布鲁 -难道我们不是吗？
-Actually, I'm Blu. -Aren't we all?
不..我是说..我的名字是Blu
No, really, that's my name.
金刚鹦鹉都是蓝色的
That's why they call us "Blue Macaws."
你就依着她吧
Just go with it.
《Welcome Back》
原来你在这种鸟里长得算是挫的
So, that's what a Blue Macaw is supposed to look like?
看她多耀眼
Look at her shining
她的羽毛闪闪发光
Her feathers, they glow
现在丛林都在欢笑
Now the jungle is smiling
因为我们的宝贝回来了
'Cause our baby's home
你是否和我一样的感受
Can you feel what I feel?
因为这一天终于来到
The day has come at last
我们心爱的珠珠回来了
Our precious Jewel has returned
我要第一个唱出来 欢迎回来
I'll be the first to sing Welcome back
罗伯特....我
Roberto. I--
欢迎回来
Welcome back
我是说 欢迎 欢迎 欢迎 欢迎
I said welcome, welcome, welcome
回来...
back
哇 你看上去棒极了
Wow, you look great!
你也是
So do you.
嗨 你好 我是珠儿...重要的那一位
Hi, hey. Hi, there. I am Jewel's significant other.
哦 你就是那个俘获了珠珠芳心的幸运鸟
So, you're the lucky bird who swept Ju-Ju off her feet.
-珠珠？  -是啊
-"Ju-Ju"? -Yeah.
我们小时候一直给对方起可爱的小名
When we were kids, we always had the cutest nicknames for each other.
是的 我叫他背头...呵呵
We did. I called him "Beto."
那真可爱 我也喜欢起小名
That's adorable. I love doing the nicknames.
你可从来没提起过什么罗伯特
You never mentioned any "Roberto."
那是他没有什么可提的啊
There's nothing to mention.
嘿
Hey.
我的搭档来了
There's my wingman!
有罗伯特放哨 我们都能安心睡觉了
We can rest easy with Roberto on the lookout.
多亏艾迪教会我一切 他是一只好鸟
Eduardo taught me everything I know. He's the bird.
-不 你才是好鸟...
No. You're the bird.
-不 你是好鸟 -你才是好鸟
-No, you're the bird. -You're the bird!
知道了 你们两个都是好鸟
We get it. You're both "the bird."
能不能别唧唧歪歪了 开始聚会吧
Now, can we stop yakking and start partying?
哇哦...我记得这首歌
Wow! I remember this song.
怎么可能忘记 它一直流淌在我们的血液里 宝贝
How could you forget? It's in our blood, baby.
这是只属于我们的歌
It's who we are.
《Beautiful Creatures》
不介意我借用她一会吧？嗯...
You don't mind if I borrow her for a minute, do you?
-额 事实上我... -来吧 珠珠
-Actually... -Come on, Ju-Ju!
开始了
Let's go!
Let's come together Singing love and harmonia
We are so different
But the same inside our hearts
Blue-tiful colors
As far as the eye can see
Open your wings
Fly when you hear the call
Let's celebrate Calling all beautiful creatures
Come spread your wings Dance and sing songs about freedom
Like la-la-la, ooh-ooh
-One for the jungle família -Come on, Blu!
Like ba-ba-ba, boom-boom
-Calling all beautiful creatures -Hey, Jewel? Jewel!
Come this way, celebrate
Laugh and dance all the way
这个地方真是潜力无穷啊 我好喜欢他们这种歌
Yo, this is untapped territory. I'm loving this sound.
Pop-Pop! I am a Pop-Pop!
I am your Pop-Pop! Yeah, I am the Pop-Pop
Hey, the Pop-Pop!
Let's celebrate Calling all beautiful creatures
Come spread your wings Dance and sing songs about freedom
Like la-la-la, ooh-ooh
One for the jungle família
Like ba-ba-ba, boom-boom
Calling all beautiful creatures
只有你能理解 孤苦伶仃是什么感觉
You're the only one who knows what it feels like to be all alone.
就这样
Misunderstood.
你邪恶 我狠毒
You're the evil to my lethal.
你应该改个名字叫话唠
I can see why they call you "Gabi."
在哪儿呢 你这个肮脏的家禽
Where are you, you filthy fowl?
站住
Halt!
我之前的行动战略不对
I've been going about this all wrong.
我应该去更高的地方找
I need to search from higher ground.
哦 你刚才腾空了将近整整一秒钟
You stayed airborne for almost a full second that time.
你看什么看 帮我上去
What are you looking at? Get me up there.
高点 高点
Higher.
再高点
Higher! Even higher.
稍微再高点
Little bit higher.
低点 现在低点
Lower. Lower, now.
很好 现在正好
Yes. Perfect.
哇哦 这么一大群祸害
It's an infestation.
呵呵 继续庆祝吧 你们很快就要高兴不起来了
Keep celebrating. I'll be pooping on your party promptly.
嗨 尼克  嗨 佩克罗
Hi, Nico! Hi, Pedro!
我们来对地方了
We came to the right place.
这就是火爆 亚马逊的火爆
This is popping. It's popping in the Amazon.
我们要把这些金刚鹦鹉带回里约
We could bring these macaws back to Rio...
参加有史以来最棒的狂欢节演出
and have the best Carnival show ever.
我现在灵感如泉涌
I am inspired!
抱歉 城里来的鸟
Sorry to break it to you, city boys...
我看你们还是去找别的明星吧
but you'll have to find some other talent.
谁也不许离开这里
Nobody leaves the tribe.
哦 还有 丛林里不许留下人类的东西 听懂了么
And no human things in the jungle. Understood?
什么 他什么毛病
What? What's his problem?
我被扒光了...
I feel naked.
差点就能流芳百世了
We could have been legends.
我们已经超级无敌了 可是...
We already are super-mega-dope, but...
你懂我的意思吗
You know what I'm saying?
我们什么都有 没被发掘的明星
We had it all. The undiscovered talent...
好的创意 灵感
the big idea, the inspiration.
可是没有办法把他们带回里约...
But if we can't bring these guys to Rio...
就什么都没有
we got nothing.
什么都没有？
Nothing?
别那么失落嘛 不是还有我老婆吗
Hold your mangoes. We still have Eva.
怎么
What?
哇哦 你跳的还是那么好 珠珠
Wow! You still got the moves, Ju-Ju.
-我快累死了 -是啊
-I'm so exhausted. -Yeah.
我们该去休息了 找个旅馆或者酒店
We should get some rest. Find a local inn, or B and B nearby.
你在胡说些什么啊
What is this crazy talk?
不 你们就住我家里
No, you guys are staying in my nest.
今晚我巡逻
I'm on patrol tonight.
我的家 就是你们的家
Mi casa es su casa.
你真是太好了 背头
That's really nice, Beto.
谢谢 但我觉得我们能搞定
Thank you, but we're fine.
再说我们一大家子 住单身公寓 挤不下
Besides, our whole family couldn't possibly fit in your bachelor pad.
哇哦
Whoa.
这里的房价一定非常低吧
Real estate must be pretty cheap around here.
哇哦 真是不可思议
Wow. This is incredible.
你说这家？这只是我最近随便弄的
This old nest? It's just something I put together last minute.
当然 用的是我的两只翅膀
With my own two wings, of course.
我的力气
And my strength.
还有我的肌肉（...）
And my brawn.
爸爸 这里好大 有六个卧室呢
Dad, it's huge! It has six bedrooms!
-我要最大的这间  -我是最大的
-I get the big one! -No! I'm the oldest.
就比我大3分钟外加2.5秒
Only by 3 minutes, 2.5 seconds.
我真希望有一天
I had hoped to one day be blessed...
我也有一群小鬼抢房间
with a flock of little Robertos to call my own.
-一定会的  -不会吧
-I bet you did. -No way!
这里有鸟浴盆
A bird bath!
迪耶戈 小...
Tiago, caref-...
还有按摩
Jacuzzi.
嘿 布鲁 跟你说点事
Blu, let me tell you something.
如果你出了任何事 任何...
If anything, and I mean anything, ever happens to you...
我会帮忙照顾好你的家人
I will take care of your family.
行了 睡个好觉
All right, buddy. Sleep well.
-晚安 珠珠   -晚安
-Good night, Ju-Ju. -Good night.
好了 一切都安全了
Okay. All clear.
Jewel：月光和星光
Moon beams and starlight
《Don't Go Away》
神奇的曙光
Magical twilight
最温暖的雨
The warmest rain
听他低吟你的名字
Hear it whispering your names?
午夜的彩虹
Rainbows at midnight
让星空闪耀
Sparkling night skies
不要远走
Don't go away
多停留一天
Stay another day
你能再唱一遍吗？
Can you sing it again, please?
该睡觉了
Time for bed, now.
多棒的一天啊
What an amazing day.
一直以来 我...
All this time...
我都没奢望过他们还活着
I never let myself hope that they were alive.
但是他们真的还都活着
But they are.
我们找到家人了 布鲁
We found our family, Blu.
这会改变一切的
This changes everything.
是的
Yeah.
等等 什么？ 改变什么？
Wait. What? What's changing?
珠儿
Jewel?
去 去  走开
Shoo, shoo, shoo. Go on.
亲爱的 别 别这样 很痒的
Honey, stop. That tickles.
哈哈 真有意思
That was fun!
迪耶戈
Tiago!
快走 迪耶戈 看我们走
Come on, Tiago. Let's go.
早上好
Morning.
或者我应该说 下午好
Or should I say "afternoon"?
早上好 先生
Morning, sir.
生活在这里得习惯早起
Our days here in the jungle, they start early.
早上好 爸爸
Morning, Daddy.
真是我的好女儿 她早就起来了
That's my girl. See? Already up and at 'em.
早上好 亲爱的
Morning, sweetie.
你干嘛让我睡懒觉
Why did you let me sleep in?
你说什么呢？你每天都睡懒觉
What are you talking about? You sleep in every day.
-是的 可是... -爸爸
-Yeah, but... -Hey, Dad.
咪咪阿姨说泥土对消化有好处
Aunt Mimi says clay is good for your digestion.
-试试啊  -不 宝贝儿 我刚刚刷...
-Try some. -No, sweetie. I just brushed my--
味道不错吧 我再去弄点
It's good, right? I'm gonna go get some more.
聪明的孩子
Smart girl.
我说要领格鲁转一转
So, I thought I'd take Louie, here, for a little tour of the area.
参观一下
Show him around.
-这主意太好了 -什么？
-That's a great idea. -What?
你跟爸爸出去转转 我带孩子们探探险
You go have fun with Daddy, and I'll explore around here with the kids.
-恩 好的 -你会喜欢的
-Yeah, okay. Sure. -You'll love it.
恩 好的 我只要...
Yeah, great. I just gotta...
行了 好了
Okay, ready.
这...
Okay...
鲁 靠近点
Lou, come closer.
-太近了 -好的
-Not so close. -Okay.
听着...
Listen...
我看不下去了 你把人类的口袋扔掉 行吗？
I can barely look at it. You gotta lose that human pocket, okay?
这只是个腰包
This is a fanny pack.
腰包嘛 很可爱
"Fanny pack." Adorable.
但这是人类的
It's human.
现在你已经是部落的一员了 你以后用不着它了
And now that you're joining the tribe, you won't be needing it anymore.
我们在河边泥岸上见
I'll meet you by the clay banks.
哦 不 加入部落？
"Joining the tribe"?
他不会以为我们真要搬到丛林里来吧
He doesn't actually think we're moving to the jungle, does he?
不 不 他是因为我们来了 太激动了
No. He's just excited we're all here.
别扫兴好么
Let's not ruin the moment, okay?
再说了 不带这个腰包去又不会要了你的命
Besides, it won't kill you to leave behind the fanny pack.
好吧 你赢了 我不带腰包就是了
All right, you win. I will leave the fanny pack behind.
老婆开心 日子舒心
Happy wife, happy li--
再见 亲爱的
Bye, honey.
玩的开心点
Have fun.
哦 当然 再见
Yeah. Sure. Bye.
各位 该起床了
You guys. Wakey-wakey!
-起床啦！ -伊娃 你有角色了
-Wake up! -Eva! You got it!
那个野性亚马逊怎么样了？
What happened to "Amazon Untamed"?
我订了计划 今天面试
Here's the plan. Auditions today...
然后明天预演一场
and we preview the show tomorrow.
我们？什么 你在说法语么？
"We"? What you talking about, "we"? You speak French?
行了 抓紧时间 我们开始吧
Come on, chop-chop. Let's get started!
哇哦 她动作可够快的
Kid's been working.
Tell me when to go Tell me when to go
Tell me when to go Tell me when to go!
'Cause shawty got low, low, low, low, low
准备好了就可以开始了
Any time you're ready.
每次碰见个男的 我就想把他追到手
Every time I come a fella gotta get it
可是他们最后都逃走了 我就装傻 我就装酷
Then I gotta go, and then I gotta get it Then they gotta blow
管他们想什么 做什么
And then I gotta show that any little thing A fella think that he be doing
我不关心 到此结束
'Cause it doesn't matter, I'm done
下一个
Next!
我们是神奇的巴西战舞龟
We are the amazing Capoeira Turtles.
原引巴西战舞卡波耶拉，一种艺术与武术之间的独特舞蹈
太精彩了 再来一个 再来一个
-Bravo! Encore! Encore! -Encore!
抱歉 伙计们 刚才谁表演
Sorry, guys. Did I miss anything?
嗨 我叫格兰纳 我是水豚
Hi, my name is Claira the capybara...
我要唱一首我最喜欢的歌
and I will be singing my favorite song.
回忆
Memory
孤零零的站在月光里
All alone in the moonlight
告诉我
Touch me
离开是如此的容易
It's so easy to leave me
再这么吃下去我们就没有演员了
If they keep eating each other, we got no show.
这里不是比谁吃的多
This ain't an all-you-can-eat competition!
嘿 你飞的好快 真的好快
Hey. You are fast. You are really, really fast.
我感觉我翅膀已经拉伤了 你这老鸟飞的还真快
I think I pulled a wing or something. You are really fast for an old bird.
我是说...你的智慧 拥有很多智慧的鸟
For such a wise bird, is what I meant to say. Wise bird.
智慧一般是随年龄一起增长的
Which sometimes comes with age...
不过年轻的时候也增长 比如像你 年轻又智慧
but also can happen when you're young, like in your case.
这种组合很少见 不过看到你这样..
You could be wise and young, which is kind of a rare combination...
真的好让人激动
but thrilling when it happens.
-安静点儿  -哦 谢谢
-Be quiet. -Thank you, sir.
你应该把城市的习惯丢掉了
It's time to shake that city off of you.
你要学习基本的...丛林生存要素
You need to learn the basics of jungle survival.
我们不是出来观光的吗？
I thought we were going sightseeing.
今天是训练日
It's training day.
来吧 泥土是你的朋友
Come on! The mud is your friend.
这是你的伪装 感觉他 品尝他
This is your camouflage! Feel it. Taste it!
如果没感觉 说明你的动作不对
If you don't feel crusty, you're not doing it right!
你不会想被人类看见的
You don't wanna be seen by humans!
快点儿 你是蓝皮克斯鹦鹉还是火鸡？
Come on! Are you a macaw or a turkey?
快点 再快点
Faster. Faster.
加油！你不想被吃掉吧
Come on! You don't wanna be eaten!
你独自一人在丛林里 你被陷阱抓住了
You're alone in the jungle. You get caught in a trap.
你会怎么办？
What do you do?
-如果我的腰包在的话  -不
If I had my fanny pack--
你要用你的嘴
No! You use your beak.
-我的嘴 -这是你最重要的工具
-My beak. -It's your most important tool.
好的 我用我的嘴
Okay, okay. No, I use my beak.
-就差一点了 -时间到
-Almost. -Time's up!
你挂了
You're jaguar meat.
罗伯特第一次就成功了
Roberto got it on the first try.
肯定的
Of course he did.
上 上 盘旋
Up, up! And hover!
-现在倒着飞 -什么 倒着飞
-Now, backwards! -What, backwards?
不 只有蜂鸟能倒着飞
No, only hummingbirds can fly backwards.
倒着飞
Backwards.
跳 飞起来 俯冲 在高点
Over! Under!Over!Under! Over!
-干得好  -谢谢
-Good job. -Thanks.
没说你
Not you.
嗨！
Hi.
这是巴西栗树
Brazil nut trees.
这些树对我们的生存至关重要
These trees are the key to our way of life.
这些树为我们提供食物
The trees feed us.
它们供养我们 他们...
They sustain us.
-醒醒 -我醒着
-Wake up! -I'm up.
栗巴西...巴西栗树什么的
Nutty Brazil... Brazil nut trees, something.
是的 明白了
Yeah, got it.
这很重要 我们要保护这些树
This is important. We have to protect these trees.
我们的未来要依靠他们
Our future depends on it.
嗨 艾迪 这跟班是谁啊
Yo, Eddie. Who is your sidekick?
你现在需要护士了？
You got a nurse now?
嗨 我是...
Hi, I'm--
你们是不是离我们的地盘太近了？
Aren't you boys getting a little bit too close to our side?
我们说好的 费利佩
We have a deal, Felipe.
嘿 别紧张
Hey, relax.
你知道我们对你满怀深情
You know we got nothing but mad love for you.
来吧 伙计们快飞吧
Come on, boys, let's fly.
给天空添些色彩吧 让他们去哭鼻子咯
Paint the sky. Before they start to cry.
-他们挺和气的   -树林那边是他们的
-They seem nice. -They have their side of the grove...
这边是我们的
and we have ours.
最近食物短缺
Food is scarce these days.
从没看见他们离我们的家园这么近
Never seen them this close to the village before.
啥？
What?
-别让他们看到你  -哦 对 抱歉
-Don't let them see you! -Right, right. Sorry.
也许我们应该去找琳达
Maybe we should go find Linda.
-那是什么？  -琳达是人 她把我养大
-What's a Linda? -Linda is the person that raised me.
-你是宠物？
What? You're a pet?
不是你想的那样 我们是朋友
No, it wasn't anything like that. I was a companion.
朋友？难怪你这幅样子
You liked it? That explains everything.
-琳达是我的家人  -家人？
-Linda is family. -Family?
人类不是我们的家人
Humans aren't family.
你没明白 他们是来帮忙的
No, you don't understand. They're coming here to help.
听着
Listen to me.
绝对不能带人类到我们的部落
We do not bring humans into the tribe.
远离人类我们才活到现在
That is the only reason we're still alive.
这你总应该明白吧
You cannot be confused about this. Understood?
是的 明白
Yeah. Got it.
现在 观光结束
Sightseeing is over.
你看见鸟巢了嚒？
Do you see the nest?
图里奥 你没事吧？
Tulio, are you okay?
我没事 我很好 我...
I'm fine! I'm okay!
我不太好
Not okay.
图里奥 他们在砍伐森林
Tulio, they're cutting down the forest!
琳达你要去哪？
Linda, where are you going?
去跟他们说 你去跟鸟说 我和人说
To talk to them. You talk to birds, I talk to humans.
不 等等
No! Wait, don't!
嘿 先生 你好
Hey! Hey, mister!
喂！
Hello!
我命令你把电锯关掉
You take it easy with that chainsaw.
有很珍贵的鸟类居住在这片丛林里 你不能把这些树都砍掉
There are rare birds living around here. You can't cut down these trees!
哦 亲爱的 你在这儿啊
Sweetheart! There you are.
我到处找你
I was looking for you.
嗨 你好 这儿真漂亮 对吗？
Hi, there. Beautiful out here, isn't it?
你们迷路了？
You two lost?
迷路？没有 呵呵
Lost? No!
迷路？
Lost?
不
No.
我们是来 来 来度蜜月的
We're here on our honeymoon.
我们正要回去和旅行团汇合呢
We're actually just heading back to join the tour.
今天是卡拉OK之夜
It's karaoke night.
走吧 亲爱的 人家还等着我们去唱..月亮河呢
Come along, honey. Moon River isn't going to sing itself.
琳达 这些人砍得可不止这些树
Linda, logs aren't the only things these guys cut.
快跑 琳达 我拖住他们
Run, Linda. I'll hold them off.
走 走 走 快跑！
-Go, go, go! Run! -Okay, okay, okay!
请让一下 让一下
Excuse me, excuse me!
来吧 我们来比赛
Come on, I'll race you.
-真是太棒了  -好样的 迪耶戈
-This is great! -All right, Tiago!
哦 耶！
Oh, yeah!
迪耶戈
Tiago!
这真是太爽了
That is so good.
嘿 你们回来啦
Hey, you're back.
玩儿的怎么样啊？
How did it go?
我们玩的很开心 今天很有教育意义
We had a great time. It was educational.
爸爸 背头叔叔教了我一些很酷的飞行技巧
Dad! Uncle Beto showed me some cool flying tricks.
叔叔？
"Uncle"?
看 我会倒着飞啦
Look, I can fly backwards.
是啊 你很有天分
Yeah, you're a natural, T-Bird.
丛林的生活技巧要从小学起
It's never too soon to learn the ways of the jungle, Tiago.
可是有些家伙学不会
Although, some may never learn.
我要去..洗个澡（可怜的blu）
I'm gonna go clean up.
罗伯特 我看见人类在丛林附近
Roberto, we saw humans near the grove.
你要保持警惕
I need you to stay alert.
丛林的生活方法..
"Ways of the jungle."
我倒想学离开的方法
I would like to learn a way out of this jungle.
哦 他在那儿 我们的机会来啦
There he is. Now is our chance.
哦 我真是太激动了
I'm so excited!
准备舌头弹弓
Prepare the tongue-a-pult.
查理 让我重新飞起来
Charlie, make me fly again.
去干掉他们 老虎
Go get them, tiger!
快向征服你的凤头鹦鹉跪拜吧
Bow before the conquering cockatoo.
你是不是有病啊 伙计？
What is your problem, dude?
天哪 好变态啊
Bird, that was sick!
我说 面试的时候就该有这种镜头
Now, that's the energy you bring into an audition.
面试？
Audition?
是啊 我就是面试的
Yeah, that's actually why I'm here.
我有一个很棒的....
I've got a great little--
您继续
Go on.
我们在寻找一个新的明星
We're looking for a new star.
明星？
Star?
你看上去很眼熟 我们是不是哪儿见过？
You look familiar. Don't I know you from somewhere?
不 不 不会的
No, I don't think so. No. I'm...
我叫...鲍勃 小鲍勃
Bob. Yes. Bob, the bird.
无所谓啦 展示才艺吧
Okay, Bob, whatever. Show us what you got.
恩 一开始我很害怕
Well, at first I was afraid
我惊得目瞪口呆
I was petrified
我一直以为我没法再活下去
I kept thinking that I could never live
没法再展翅飞翔
I could barely fly
我在无数个慢慢长夜里回想
And I spent, oh, so many nights
回想起他对我的残忍
thinking how he did me wrong
于是我变得坚强
And I grew strong
我学会了如何随遇而安
And I learned how to get along
《I Will Survive》
走吧 快滚 滚出这扇门
Go on, now, go Walk out the door
转身离开吧
Just turn around now
现在这里是我的了
It is I who have the floor
你不就是那个想用分手来伤害我的人吗？
Weren't you the one who tried to hurt me with goodbye?
-你以为我会垮掉  -哦 不
-Did you think I'd crumble? -Oh, no!
你以为我会躺在这儿死掉？
Did you think I'd lay down and die?
-不 奈杰尔你不会  -我会活下来
Oh, no, not Nige
只要我知道怎么去恨 我就会活下来
I will survive As long as I know how to hate
我会好好过这一生
I know I'll stay alive I've got all my life to live
我又满腔的爱要付出
And I've got all my love to give
-我会活下来  -你会活下来
-And I will survive -You will survive
-我会活下来  -我们会活下来
-I will survive -We will survive
我是个幸存者 我的眼睛虎视眈眈
I'm a survivor I've got the eye of a tiger
加强修炼 多吃高纤
Been training again And eating my fiber
你只是活着 而我是鲜活的活着
You been staying alive Well, I've been staying alive-er
你要坐稳了 我吐口水的时候声音响彻云霄
Watch where you sit when I spit my saliva, like boom
你从来没见过一只凤头鹦鹉
You've never seen a cockatoo
随着摇滚的节奏 又唱又跳 尽情摇摆
Rocking and shocking and dropping And popping and locking, too?
看看我的本事 都用不着调音器
Watch what I can do Without no Auto-Tune
怎么样
Say what?
真的没有用哦
Oh, no, he didn't.
如果你你打压我
If you try to keep me down
只会让我变得更坚强
I'll just come back stronger
你想打断我
You try to cut me short
只会让我说的更多
I'll just come back longer
如果你想用乒乓球打败我 我会变成乒乓球健将
If you beat me at ping pong I'll just play ping pong-er
给我个王位 我准备好上位
Give me my throne, I am ready to thrive
我很清楚一件事
One thing I know
我会活下去
I will survive
我会...活下去
谢谢 我是小鸟 鲍勃
Yes, thank you. I've been Bob the bird.
他真是太帅了
He is so hot.
好了 就是他 我要了
Boom. That's it. You in.
虽然不如伊娃 但是你很棒
You're no Eva, but you're awesome.
明天晚上狂欢节演出的时候见
We'll see you at the performance tomorrow night.
这里所有的鸟都会来看 你一定会红到发紫的
Everyone from the village is coming. It's gonna be off the charts.
所有鸟
Everyone?
这是个完美的计划
It's the perfect plan.
算你运气好 拔你几根刺 豪猪
Be happy we're only plucking you, porcupine.
滚吧
Go away.
与其满林子追那只鸟
Instead of chasing that bird all over the jungle...
不如让他演出的时候自己送上门
we let him come to us, at the Carnival show.
我会在舞台上迷住他们 而在观众席里...
I'll mesmerize them from the stage, while in the audience...
你 我的小噶比...
you, my little Gabi...
你会成为我的 迷你致命武器
you'll be my petite weapon of mass destruction.
这场演出将会是..
It will be a performance...
好看到死
to die for.
只有我才笑得出那种气场
It only works when I do it.
好的 爱你哦
Okay. Love you.
啊...舒服
So minty.
好耶
Yes!
哦 亲爱的 你在这儿 怎么这么长时间？
Hey, sweetie, there you are. What's taking you so long?
啊 别再弄那个GPS了
Enough with that GPS, really.
我们一起去看日落 快走吧
The whole tribe's gathering to watch the sunset. Come on.
等一下 我刚找到琳达和图里奥的坐标
No, no. Hang on. I just found Linda and Tulio's coordinates.
他们就在林子的另一半 瞧
They are just on the other side of the grove.
他们离得很近
Look, they're really close.
是呀
Yeah.
我知道你爸爸不相信人类
Now, I know your dad doesn't totally trust humans...
可他一旦见到了 他就会改变想法
but I'm sure if he met them, he would change his mind.
琳达他们能保护这里
They can help keep this place safe.
是的 布鲁..
Yeah, Blu...
我爸自己能解决
my dad knows what he's doing.
我说你能不能忘掉琳达和图里奥一会儿 好好享受日落？
And can't you just forget Linda and Tulio for one minute and enjoy a sunset?
但是这不是我们的计划吗？
But I thought that was our plan.
GPS:路线规划完成
GPS: Route guidance complete.
恩...我...你知道 有些地方也许不该被发现
You know, maybe some places shouldn't be found.
也许就应该与世隔绝
Maybe they should just be left alone.
她吃了一只虫子 一只虫子
She ate a bug. A bug!
布鲁 布鲁 冷静
Blu, Blu, Blu! Calm down.
冷静？我们有个计划
Calm down? We had a plan.
帮助琳达和图里奥找到鹦鹉 然后回家
Help Linda and Tulio find the flock and get home.
可是我提醒他 她根本就不理我
But when I mentioned it to her, she completely shut me down.
哦 还有他的爸爸 完全不开窍
And her father? A total nut job.
他对人类的看法很奇怪
He's got this weird thing about humans.
He's got this weird thing about humans!
他爱人类 他是个宠物
He loves them. He's a pet!
宠物？
A pet?
他叫我宠物！
He called me a pet.
真不敢相信 他居然当我的面这么说
I can't believe he used the "P" word to my face.
像是把我当成敌人似的
It's like he thinks I'm the enemy or something.
他跟我们不是一路的 你要盯着点儿他
He's not one of us, Roberto. Keep an eye on him.
还有那个罗伯特 他在监视
And that Roberto? He is always watching.
总是在珠儿身边转 总是唱着什么歌
He is always hovering around Jewel. He is always singing something.
我根本比不上他
I can't compete with that.
你要拿出点鸟样来
You gotta bird up, bird!
从被驯养的状态中解放出来
You gotta emancipate yourself from domestication.
用珠儿的眼光看这里
Try to see this place through her eyes.
去尝尝珠儿品尝的那些味道
Taste the flavors she's tasting.
让我去吃虫子？
So I should eat a bug?
那太恶心了 再考虑一下
That's just nasty, thinking about it.
闪光片 我的闪光片在哪儿？
Glitter. Where is my glitter?
哦 对不起 对不起
I'm sorry. Sorry.
我不需要听道歉 我要闪光片
I don't want apologies. I want glitter.
充满魔力的表演最终要靠的就是闪光片
Glitter is absolutely essential for a magical performance.
-你怎么就不懂呢？ -伙计们
-Do you know nothing? -Guys!
快去彩排 明天是个大日子
Rehearsals, big day tomorrow.
想起来了吗？ 你回来的 对吗 爸爸？
Ring a bell? Come on. You're coming, right, Dad?
哦 当然了
Oh, yeah, of course.
那孩子把娱乐搞得像是交作业
That girl put the "business" in "show business."
-布鲁 记住
Blu, remember--
我知道 我知道了 老婆开心 日子舒心
I know, I know. Happy wife, happy life.
多么美好的晨曦啊！
What a glorious morning!
我都忘记了能够享受这样的早晨
I forgot I could have mornings like this.
耶
Yeah.
你最爱吃的
Your favorite.
哦 你记得这个
You remembered.
这真是太好了
Isn't that nice?
这感觉真是棒极了
It's so crazy good.
谢谢你 布鲁
Thank you so much, Blu.
对呀
That's it!
我要给珠儿一个惊喜
I'll be the one to surprise her.
给他送早餐 马上就来
Breakfast in bed, coming up.
巴西栗
Brazil nuts.
你们在哪儿？
Where are you?
我就知道你们在这附近
I know you're around here somewhere.
嘿 嘿 嘿
Hey! Hey.
不 快回来 等等
No! Come back here. Wait!
不！
No!
那不是玩具
That's not a toy.
GPS:违章驾驶 靠边停车
GPS: Erratic driving. Pull over.
不 不 不要
No, no. Don't do it.
抓到你了
I got you!
谢谢
Thank you.
总算找到了
Finally!
巴西栗
Brazil nuts.
这个才是我最重要的工具
This is my most important tool.
好啊 好啊 瞧瞧这是谁来了
Well, well, well. What do we have here?
看样子不是所有的鸟都遵守老艾迪的规矩
I guess old Eddie's rules don't apply to everyone.
这儿是我们的地盘
You're on our side.
哦 是吗？ 对不起 我的错
Really? Okay, my bad.
我没注意到 真抱歉
I didn't know that. Sorry.
对不起 对不起
Sorry! Sorry.
闯进我们的地盘 抢我们的食物
You come over here, take our food...
现在你还侮辱我？
and now you insult me?
不 不 不 这件事儿完全是个误会
No, no, no. This is all just a big misunderstanding.
知道吗 我非常想接受你的道歉
You know, I wish I could accept your apology.
你看上去像是只好鸟
You seem like a nice bird.
可是这代表战争！
But this means war!
什么？有必要吗？能代表点别的吗？
What? Does it have to? Can it mean something else?
今天 在死亡坑
Today, in the Pit of Doom.
对不起 死亡坑 真的吗？
Sorry, the "Pit of Doom"? Really?
真的么？
Really?
正午 我要腾出点地方来
High noon. I'll make some room.
像扫帚一样把你扫出这片林子
Sweep you up like a broom.
-你干了什么？
You did what?
那是个意外
It was an accident.
-意外  -嘿 出了什么事？
-An accident? -Hey, what's going on?
多谢布鲁 我们可能要失去这片林子了
Thanks to Drew, here, we could lose our entire side of the grove.
我只是想去摘个坚果  就一个
I was just trying to get a nut. One nut!
你都不喜欢吃坚果 这到底是怎么一回事 布鲁？
You don't even like nuts! What's gotten into you, Blu?
我想给你准备早点
I was getting it for you.
哦 真的吗？
You were?
罗伯特 你带上最棒的鸟去
Roberto, I want your best birds on this.
我们绝不能不战而降
We are not giving up without a fight.
明白
Got it.
你 别管这事儿了
You. Stay out of it.
净添麻烦
You've done enough.
-等等  -布鲁 他是对的
-Wait! -Blu, he's right.
就让爸爸和罗伯特去处理这件事吧
Maybe you should just let Dad and Roberto handle it.
你也觉得我处理不了？
You don't think I can do this?
不 我只是...
No, I just don't know...
只是不太确定 外交在不在你的专长范围内
if it's your exact area of expertise.
快走 快走 死亡坑
Let's go, let's go, let's go! Pit of Doom, now!
无线电！
Radio!
我希望你别介意
I hope you don't mind.
我把这儿当自己家
I made myself at home.
棒棒糖？
Lollipop?
真是可惜啊 你们两位大老远跑来保护这片森林
It's a shame, really. You came all this way to protect the jungle.
我们看看它会不会报答你们
Let's see if it will return the favor.
两个疯子...
Tree huggers.
罗伯特
Roberto.
费利佩
Felipe.
给他点厉害瞧瞧
No mercy!
我得阻止他们
I have to stop this.
什么 布鲁？
What? Blu!
停下 停下
Stop! Stop!
艾迪 这太疯狂了
Eduardo, this is crazy.
我们是高等物种 我们能更好的解决问题
We are an intelligent species with advanced problem-solving capabilities.
这是你挑起来的 等着瞧吧
You brought this on us. Now, watch.
头冲上
Heads.
尾巴冲上
Tails.
我讨厌这个工作
I hate this job.
这是比赛？ 这是比赛！
It's a game. It's a game!
这不是比赛 这是战争
It's not a game! It's war.
今天死亡坑天气不错
It's a beautiful day in the Pit of Doom!
这是胜者为王的比赛
It's winner take all!
七局四胜
It's the best of seven.
获胜者将得到整片巴西栗子林
The winner will take control of the entire Brazil nut grove!
这就像足球 这我会玩
It's just like soccer. I can do this.
好的 有什么特别战术吗？
All right, any special strategies?
打算怎么踢？4-4-2 还是 5-4-1
What are we running at, 4-4-2 or a 5-4-1?
准备好了 教练 我踢什么位置
What are we doing here, coach? What position do I play?
事实上我给你准备了一个合适的位置
Actually, I do have a perfect spot for you.
水 这儿有水 来喝水吧
Water. Water here. Get your water.
好的 谢谢
Okay, thanks.
罗伯特 他所向披靡势不可挡 到处都是他的身影
Roberto is unstoppable! He's incredible! He's everywhere!
加油罗伯特
Go, Roberto!
哼 这我也能行
I could have done that.
罗伯特和对手保持距离
Roberto springs free!
他正在向前冲 向前冲 射门了
There he goes, there he goes, there he goes! He shoots!
球进了！
Goal!
进啦！
哦 费利佩抢到了球
Felipe has the ball. The Red Macaws...
红金刚鹦鹉要扭转局面
are making a comeback.
费利佩传给提科 提科传给马里奥
Felipe pass to Tito. Tito with Mario.
马里奥传给凯撒 凯撒传给安东尼
Mario with Cesar. Cesar to Antonio.
费利佩射门得分！
Felipe scores!
嘿 去你的吧
Yes! In your face!
费利佩 罗伯特 费利佩 罗伯特...
Felipe, Roberto. Roberto, Felipe. Roberto, Felipe. Felipe, Roberto!
进球了
Goal!
这一定很疼
That has got to hurt.
上 上
Go, go!
费利佩 利佩 利佩
Felipe-lipe-lipe!
嘿
Hey!
犯规
Foul!
得了吧 裁判
Come on, ref!
好吧 你上
Okay, you're in.
真的?
Really?
没说你 你
Not you. You.
学着点吧..送水小子
Watch and learn...water boy
好吧  你  你上吧
All right, just get in there.
好的
Yes!
开始吧 教练
Okay. Here we go, coach.
嘿 爸爸
Yeah, Dad!
现在有位替补队员上场了 他会是秘密武器吗？
A new player is coming off the bench. Is he a secret weapon?
他不就是那个送水的吗
I think it's the water boy.
没人防我
Hey, I'm open!
没人防我 把球传给我啊
I'm open, toss it to me!
传给我 我这儿没人防守 快传给我啊
Hey, pass to me, I'm open. I'm wide open!
把球传给我
Pass the ball to me!
谢谢你把球传给我
Thanks for the pass, Blu!
借用一下
Mind if I borrow this?
罗伯特向前挺进 他避开一个防守
Roberto moves in. He shakes one...
又避开一个
then another!
罗伯特
Roberto!
进啦
Goal!
噢耶! 噢耶
Oh, yeah! Oh, yeah!
目前的比分 3比3
We are tied in the Pit of Doom.
接下来谁先进球
Whoever scores next...
谁就赢得比赛
wins it all!
我来接 我来接
I got it, I got it!
加油 布鲁
Come on, Blu.
哇 送水小子突然表现出了专业水准
Wow! The water boy is suddenly playing like a pro!
把球传给罗伯特
Pass the ball to Roberto!
快传球  快传球！
Pass the ball! Pass the ball!
-布鲁 等等  -我自己能搞定
-Blu, wait! -No, this bird's got it covered.
球进了!
Goal!
看上去这个秘密武器 突然走火了
It looks like the secret weapon just backfired!
我们来看看艾迪现在的反应
Let's go to Eduardo for his reaction.
我要杀了这只该死的宠物
I'm gonna kill you, fanny pack!
哦 老艾迪
Check it out, old Eddie.
看样子你们没有坚果吃了 只能减肥了
Looks like you guys are going to have to start a nut-free diet.
这场比赛在我们那儿会传为佳话的
We're gonna be talking about that for a long time.
我真不该对人类的宠物报抱什么希望
I should never have expected more from a human's pet.
嘿
Hey.
嘿 刚才你怎么回事儿啊？
What happened back there?
我太想融入这个大家庭了
I was trying to be one of the tribe.
但我可能永远都不能成为你爸爸希望的那样了
But I guess I'm never gonna be "the bird" like your dad wants me to be.
-你..说什么？ -我想我们该回家了
-What? -I think it's time to go home.
-我正要跟你说呢
We should talk about this.
说什么？
Talk about what?
布鲁 看看周围
Blu, look around.
孩子们这里 在野外玩的这么的开心
The kids are thriving. They love being in the wild.
也许这里就是我们的家
Maybe this place is home.
我们的家？ 这里是我们的家？
Home? How could this be home?
我尽全力适应这里 帮助他们..
I have done everything I can to fit in and help out...
可我做什么都不对
but no matter what I do, it's wrong.
这不是我们的家 珠儿
That's not home, Jewel.
也许属于你 但不是我的
Maybe for you, but not for me.
知道吗？你应该清楚你到底需要什么
You know what? You need to figure out what you want.
而且 别老想着你自己 也为我们想想吧
And maybe, stop thinking about just yourself and start thinking about us.
出发 出发 快点
Move out! Let's go!
太美妙了
Beautiful.
琳达 图里奥
Linda! Tulio!
再见 琳达
Goodbye, Linda.
再见 小腰包
Goodbye, fanny pack.
请在能拐弯的时候拐弯
Turn around when possible.
抱歉 GPS小姐 不是你的错 是我的不对
Sorry, GPS lady. It's not you. It's me.
再见 煎饼 再见 咖啡
Goodbye, pancakes. Goodbye, coffee.
再见 咖啡
Goodbye, coffee.
琳达？
Linda?
琳达
Linda!
艾迪说的对
Eduardo was right!
-你是个叛徒 -等等 你不明白
-Traitor! -Wait, you don't understand.
我有什么不明白的 与人类为伍？
What don't I understand? Siding with humans?
你对人类了解多少？
What do you even know about humans?
哦 我很了解他们 他们引诱你 把你抓起来
I know everything. They lure you in, they trap you.
他们还给你洗脑！
They destroy your mind!
鹦鹉要吃饼干吗 要吃饼干吗？
Polly want a cracker? Polly want a cracker?
不 我受够饼干了
No! Enough crackers!
我讨厌饼干
I hate crackers!
快走 罗伯特
Come on, Roberto!
是他们 是他们
It's them. It's them!
是他们！
It's them!
罗伯特 让开！
Roberto, get out of--
不要 不要 我不要饼干
Not again! Not again! No more crackers!
你冷静点
Snap out of it!
听好 我们有个机会阻止这一切
Look...we've got one chance to stop this, okay?
我去找到我的朋友
I have to find my friends.
你飞回去警告大家 明白吗？
You fly back and warn the others. You got it?
好 明白
Yeah. I got it.
-那好 快去 -好的
-Okay. Go! -Okay!
人类 人类
Humans, humans!
-往你的左边 不右边 右边  -我的左边？
-Your left! Your right! -My left?
左边还是右边？
Left or right?
你的右腿 我的左腿
-Your right leg, my left leg. -Okay.
很好 很好
Good! Good! Good!
-现在往上爬 -加油
-Now, go up. -Go up.
使劲
Reach!
差一点了 就快到了
Almost there!
琳达
Linda...
我真的很抱歉
I'm so sorry.
虽然情况很糟糕
As bad as this is...
但是我全世界哪儿也不想去 只想和你在一起
there is no place I would rather be in the whole world than with you.
哪怕是被拴在一棵树上 （第一部里Jewel和blu）
Even if it is tied to a tree.
哦 琳达
Linda!
布鲁！
Blu!
-琳达？  -下面！
-Linda? -Down here!
啊 布鲁
What? Blu!
你怎么在这儿 这儿很危险
What are you doing here? This is dangerous!
真难以置信 里约飞到这儿有2000英里
That's incredible! It's a 2,000-mile flight!
-我们跟着他  -太神奇了
-Let's follow him! -It's amazing!
我就说我听到他的声音了
I told you I heard him.
钥匙归我了
I'll take those.
ps：好有Avatar的感觉
一切都完了
Game over! It's over!
人类 那些光 不...
Humans! The lights!
全完了
It's over!
自从我们找到他 他就不停的说胡话
He's been blabbering like this since we found him.
伐木工来了 布鲁和他们在一起
The loggers are coming! And Blu is with them!
-他是个叛徒  -不
-Traitor! -No!
不 布鲁想帮助我们
No, Blu is trying to help us.
什么？ 就他自己？
What? By himself?
我们快撤 离开这里
Let's evacuate! We're leaving.
撤退 所有的鸟立刻出发
Let's go. Everyone move out.
-快快快 -爸爸？
-Go, go, go! -Dad?
这次不行 我不能和你一起走
No, not this time. I'm not going with you.
你必须和我一起走 我不能再让家人面临危险
You have to go with me! I will not put my family in danger again.
布鲁也是我的家人 我不会丢下他的
Blu is my family, and I'm not leaving him behind.
不用担心
You don't have to.
你没事吧
Are you okay?
听着 埃德沃德 也许我不是这里最有鸟样的鸟
Look, Eduardo, I might not be the birdliest bird in the flock...
就现在来说 这是好事
but, for once, that's actually a good thing.
你了解丛林
You know the jungle...
我了解人类
I know humans.
我们合作就能阻止伐木工
And I know that, together, we can stop them.
不能让他们夺走我们的家园
We can't let them take our home.
虽然这里又热又吵 到处是恐怖的虫子
Sure, it's hot and loud and filled with creepy bugs...
可这是属于我们的
but it's ours.
我们要为他而战 谁跟我去？
Let's fight for it. Who's with me?
我跟你..
I'm with you!
还有别人吗？
Anybody else?
停下 停下
Stop! Stop!
停下！
Stop!
停下！Stop!
哦 这就对了 请尊重热带雨林
Yeah. Respect the rainforest!
我就知道  我就知道 我就...
I knew it! I knew it!
你这是要去哪儿？
Hey. Where do you think you're going?
那只不过是一群该死的鸽子
It's just a bunch of pigeons.
给我回去干活
Get back to work!
你带头 布鲁
Lead the way, Blu.
终于叫对了 你叫我布鲁
That's my name! Yes! You called me Blu.
对 我叫布鲁！
Yes, I am Blu!
哦 对的
What? Right.
有蓝色羽毛的鸟
Birds of blue feathers...
要团结在一起
Have to stick together!
准备好了吗？ 现在往下
Everybody ready? And under!
往上
Over!
倒飞！
Backwards!
我会活下去 我会活下去
I will survive I will survive
-抓到了   -哇 好准
-Got him! -Wow, precise.
我才不怕什么鸟呢
I ain't afraid of no birds.
进攻
Attack!
亚马逊保卫战现在开始
It's on in the Amazon.
预备 扔
All right, hit it!
击掌
High-five!
为什么？为什么？
Why? Why?
给我振作起来
Get a grip!
炮弹来了
Incoming!
停下
Halt!
他在那儿
There he is.
查理 给我准备鼻射炮
Charlie, prepare the nose-zooka.
迪耶戈
Tiago!
这才对嘛
Now we're talking.
准备 瞄准
Ready...aim...
开火
fire!
又失手了
Foiled again.
-干得好 迪耶戈  -我们是最棒的团队
-Good job, Tiago. -We're a great team, Dad!
-嘿 老艾迪？ -费利佩
-Hey, old Eddie. -Felipe.
你觉得我会错过这个好机会吗？比赛开始！
You think I would miss this party? Game on!
嘿 快回来
Hey! Come back!
一群饭桶 没用的东西
You're useless, all of you!
小心
Look out!
要打架 找个个子和你一样大的
Pick on someone your own size.
不 不
No! No!
接住你了 我接住你了 没事了 你安全了
I got you, I got you. It's okay, you're safe now.
那就是琳达
That's a Linda.
耶！
Yeah!
还是这么默契 布鲁
We still got it, Blu!
真是的 什么事都得我亲自干
I have to do everything myself.
给我滚开
Hey! Get away from that!
不 没有人可以抢我的戏
No! No one steals my scene.
棒棒糖？
Lollipop?
什么？
What?
你在干嘛？ 快走
What are you doing? Let go!
快逃命吧
Save yourself!
快点 放手！
Come on, let go!
-我就不！ -你疯了吗？
-Never! -Are you crazy?
你会把我们两个都害死的
You'll bring both of us down! Let go!
飞呀！
Fly!
似曾相识吧 布鲁（法语）
Déjà vu, Blu.
奈杰尔
Nigel!
布鲁
Blu!
奈杰尔
Nigel!
你
You.
你要为你的罪恶付出最惨痛的代价
You will pay a painful price for your pestilence!
住手 别过来
Hey, stop that! Get off of me!
用我愤怒的羽毛 扇肿你的脸
A flurry of furious feathers in your face!
你没必要 没必要这么做
You don't have to do this!
我就是想这么做
No, I just want to.
嘿 停下来
Hey, stop! Stop!
哦 天哪 查理 机会来了
Oh, my goodness. Charlie! This is it. This is it!
稳住 稳住
Steady. Steady.
扇耳光比赛
Slap fight!
就是现在 发射！
Shoot! Shoot!
奈杰尔
Nigel!
我就要死了吗？
Is this the end?
我太年轻...
I was too young...
又太英俊 天妒英才
too beautiful to live.
-鲍勃  -等下 那不是鲍勃
-Bob? -Hold up! That ain't Bob!
我就说我见过他
I told you I knew him from somewhere.
这是我最后的谢幕
My final curtain call.
现在只剩下站票了
And it's standing room only.
再见
Goodbye.
不！
No!
不！！我干了些什么啊
No! What have I done?
如果不能与汝同生
If I cannot liveth with thee...
那我不如死了算了
then I shall not liveth at all.
那只青蛙它没有毒
That frog is not poisonous.
什么？
What?
我们没有死？
We're not dead?
这个品种经常被搞错 它是只假的箭毒蛙
It's a very common mistake. But she's a harmless pseudo-dendrobates.
从它粉色的斑点就能看出来
You can tell by the pink spots.
可我父母从小告诉我说 我有剧毒 叫我别碰任何人
But my parents always told me I was poisonous and shouldn't touch anyone.
你是你爸妈充话费送的吧？
You just had really mean parents.
哇哦
Oh, wow.
那么现在...So, now...
我们可以在一起啦
we can be together!
-奈杰尔 奈杰尔 我的维克多  -不
-Nigel! Nigel-Wigel-Wigglepuss! -No!
-谁来救救我！ -再也不会让你离开了
-Somebody, help me! -I'm going to never let you go.
-我绝对不会放你走的  -不 不 我会学好的
-I'm sorry, I'll be nicer. No! -Never gonna let you go!
不 查理
No, Charlie!
查理
Charlie!
这是违反自然法则的
This is unnatural!
嘿 伙计们 嗨
Hey, guys! Hi!
头发没弄脏吧？好的
There's nothing in my hair, right? Okay.
我们从亚马逊的腹地...
Directly from the heart of the Amazon rainforest...
为你带来特大新闻
we have some breaking news.
多亏了图里奥博士和他的团队
Thanks to Dr. Monteiro and his team...
这里的整片区域都将会划定为 国家野生鸟类保护区
the entire area will be designated as a National Wildlife Refuge.
我们大家会一起确保这里的安全
And together, we'll make sure this place stays safe.
对吗？布鲁？
Right, Blu?
好消息还不止这一个
But that's not the only good news.
我们在丛林深处找到这只凤头鹦鹉
We found this cockatoo deep in the Amazon...
他好像和一只树蛙黏在一起
and he seems to have bonded with a tree frog.
我们会把它带回里约 进行持续的观察
We are bringing them back to Rio for continuing observation.
哦 奈杰尔 我们要去里约度蜜月啦
Oh, Nigel! Wow! A honeymoon in Rio!
大家一起来 拍手 拍手 摇尾巴...
Put your paws, talons and tails together...
这是丛林有史以来最强大的明星阵容
for the most amazing talent ever gathered in one jungle.
下面请看--野性亚马逊
It's "Amazon Untamed!"
来 动起来
Come on! Get up!
《Batucada Familia》
嘿 嘿 别咬我 别咬我
What's up? Don't bite it What's up? Don't bite it
我的鸟儿朋友们
Where my birds at?
无论去哪儿我们都在一起
We're together no matter Where we might go
翅膀挥舞起来
Flap your wings!
团结让我们走的更远
If we're not all together We can't go far
亚马逊
Amazon!
这是我们最爱的绿宝石
It's an emerald we treasure
从密林来到你的面前
Coming from the jungle to you
拍打的是心跳的节奏
Beating like its heart beats
演绎的是自由的音符
Playing rhythms we've grown to
这是我们最美的绿宝石
It's the emerald we treasure
来自我们生活的地方
-Coming from the place where we live -The place where we live
充满自由和欢乐的家园
-The home of freedom and happiness -Happiness
时光不停飞逝 丛林就像一阵清风 一个奇迹
Time flies forever The jungle's like a breeze, it's a wonder
快穿上舞裙 随时有人叫你跳舞
Now get out your tutu In case someone wants you to dance
-你好 亚马逊 -嘿 路易兹
-Hello, Amazon! -Hey, Luiz!
-嘿 小鸟们 我来了 -欢迎来到雨林 狗哥
-Hey birds, I made it! -Welcome to the jungle, dawg!
战舞龟 巴西战舞龟
All my turtles! Hardcore turtles!
唱吧 宝贝儿
Sing it, baby!
拉斐尔！
Rafi!
你确定要在亚马逊安家吗？
Are you sure you can make the Amazon our home...
这里有热又有恐怖的虫子
with the heat and the creepy bugs?
开什么玩笑 我可是丛林先生
Are you kidding? I am Mr. Jungle.
充满野性而且还很有鸟样
Totally wild, and very birdly.
夏天还是去里约避暑吧
Maybe we can do summers in Rio.
你是我的唯一 珠儿
You're my one and only, Jewel.
---狸猫制作 谢谢观赏---
结束了吗？
That's the end?
《Rio Rio (feat. B.o.B)》